JAVAD BAYAZI

Montreal, Quebec, Canada

■ Email: mohammad.bayazi@mila.quebec in LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/mjdarvishi

③Google Scholar: scholar.google.com/citations → GitHub: github.com/MohammadJavadD

𝚱Website: mohammadjavadd.github.io/home

Profile

Driven by curiosity and an analytical mindset, I bring a fresh perspective to any Machine Learning team. My experience spans research, teaching, and leading teams in AI-focused projects. I'm experienced in developing deep learning models and excel at managing multiple responsibilities, from academia to entrepreneurship.

Technical Skills

Programming languages: Python, C, Matlab, R, Bash, SQL

Developer Tools: Git, PyTest, Docker, VS Code, Jupyter Notebook, Unix shell,

Data Mining and Machine Learning:PyTorch, TensorFlow, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn

Technologies/Frameworks: Wandb, HuggingFace, Hydra, Slurm, Cluster, HPC

Cloud: Google Cloud Platform, Amazon Web Services (AWS SageMaker)

Domain: Computer Vision (CV), Natural Language Processing (NLP), Generative AI, Large Language Models (LLMs),

Large Multimodal Models (LMMs), Foundation Models, Time Series

Work Experience

Mila - Quebec Artificial Intelligence Institute

Jan. 2019 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant - PhD Student

Montreal, Canada

- Designed and deployed large-scale foundation models for time series forecasting. These models inherently possess zero-shot capabilities, requiring no further tuning for immediate application.
- Developed and implemented strategies and benchmarks to enhance the robustness and reliability of deep learning models, effectively addressing real-world challenges to ensure safe and dependable machine learning deployment.
- Published 3 peer-reviewed articles in highly ranked journals, 5 papers in top-tier conferences, and preprints, which have been widely utilized in subsequent research and projects.
- Collaborated and communicated effectively with multidisciplinary teams (CAE, NRC, Marinvent and Morgan Stanley) to translate research findings into actionable and scalable solutions for several industries.

NBML - National Brain Mapping Laboratory

2017 - 2018

Signal Processing Engineer

Tehran, Iran

- Developed pipelines for researchers, doctors, and practitioners to study brain function and develop therapeutic methods.
- Analyzed various types of signals and images using computational tools to facilitate clinical decision-making.
- Performed statistical analysis on diverse datasets to identify trends and patterns in various metrics.

Hummingbird - AI startup

July, 2022 - Present

Chief Executive Officer

Montréal, Canada

• Leading development of foundation models for time series analysis, enabling more accurate planning and decision-making in finance, economics, governance, and medicine.

Education

University of Montreal (UMontréal - Mila (Quebec Artificial Intelligence Institute))

2019 - Present

Doctor of Philosophy in Biomedical Engineering (Machine Learning)

Montreal, Canada

- Topic: R3: Robust and Reliable Deep Learning Models for Real-World Applications
- Supervisors: Jocelyn Faubert (UdeM, FaubertLab), Irina Rish (UdeM, Mila)

Shahed University

2014 - 2018

Master of Science in Biomedical Engineering - Bioelectrics

Tehran, Iran

• Topic: Causality and Information Flow in Multivariate Time Series

Yazd University

2010 - 2014

Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering

Yazd, Iran

• Topic: Smart Greenhouse Monitoring and Control System Using Industrial Microprocessors

Coursework and Certificate

- Deep Representation Learning
- Artificial Neural Network
- Biomedical Systems Modeling

- Generative AI with LLMs
- Digital Signal and Image Processing
- Microcontrollers

- Statistical Pattern Recognition
- Nonlinear Dynamics and Chaos
- SQL for Data Science

Selected Publications

- Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., ..., Faubert, J., & Rish, I. (2023). Amplifying Pathological Detection in EEG Signaling Pathways through Cross-Dataset Transfer Learning. CIBM, [Link, IF:7.7, Acceptance Rate:13%]
- Rasul, K., Ashok, A., ..., Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., ..., & Rish, I. (2024). Lag-Llama: Towards Foundation Models for Probabilistic Time Series Forecasting. [Link]
- Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., Law, A., Romero, S. M., Jennings, S., Rish, I., & Faubert, J. (2023) Beyond performance: The role of task demand, effort, and individual differences in ab initio pilots. Scientific Reports. [Link, IF:4.9]
- Gagnon-Audet, J. C., Ahuja, K., Darvishi-Bayazi, M. J., Dumas, G., & Rish, I. (2023) WOODS: Benchmarks for Out-of-Distribution Generalization in Time Series Tasks. TMLR, ICLR 2024. [Link, Featured]
- Albuquerque I, Monteiro J, Darvishi M, Falk TH, & Mitliagkas I. (2019) Generalizing to unseen domains via distribution matching. arXiv preprint arXiv:1911.00804. [Link]
- Ghaffari, H., Yoonessi, A., Darvishi, M. J., & Ahmadi, A. (2018). Normal electrical activity of the brain in obsessive-compulsive patients after anodal stimulation of the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. Basic and clinical neuroscience, 9(2), 135. [Link]

Interest

- Artificial Intelligence (AI)
- Machine Learning (ML)
- Deep Learning (DL)
- Representation Learning
- Self-Supervised Learning (SSL)
- Out of Distribution Generalization
- Transfer Learning
- Cognitive Neuroscience
- AI for Health
- Brain-Computer Interface (BCI)
- Information retrieval
- Human in Loop

Teaching Activity

UdeM/Mila

Jan. 2022 – May 2022

Teaching Assistant at IFT 6135 - Representation Learning - SSL, NLP, CV

Montreal, Canada

- Assisted Dr. Aaron Courville, a pioneer in AI and deep learning, in teaching self-supervised learning techniques.
- Provided support to students by addressing questions and assisting with coding issues during the course.

Ivado/Mila

Mar. 2021 - Apr. 2021

Teaching Assistant at Deep Learning Spring School

Montreal, Canada

 Assisted machine learning practitioners from various industries in understanding and implementing advanced deep learning techniques.

Honors & Awards

Artificial Intelligence Applications in Healthcare

2021

Microsoft Diversity Award

2020

Bourse d'exemption des droits de scolarité supplémentaires

2019 - 2020

Master's Thesis Research Grants from Cognitive Science and Technologies Council

2018

Distinguished Student, Ranked 1^{th} among all graduated students of Biomedical Engineering department

2018

Ministry of Science and Technology scholarship (7 years, BSc, MSc)

2010 - 2017

Leadership / Extracurricular

President, Vice-president and Webmaster

Sep. 2019 - Jan. 2024

staem, vice-president and weomaster

IEEE

- Organized AI4Good event and the AI against COVID-19 competition, raised 20K⁺ CAD from Microsoft Canada
- Designed and launched the website of the group

1^{st} and 2^{nd} IBCIC

SIGHT Montreal

Jan. 2017 - 2018

Vice-Chair of the Executive Committee

NBML

• Designed a Brain-computer Interface competition, TV Report

Languages

English, Proficient | Persian, Native | French, Beginner